JOSHUA MEYER

joshua.richard.meyer@gmail.com

jrmeyer.github.io

 \odot

Josh is a leader working at the intersection of data, machine learning, generative AI, and language. With over a decade of experience, his career has spanned from large corporations to start-ups, from academia to non-profits. With a PhD in automatic speech recognition, Josh deeply understands the technical underpinnings of AI. He has lead teams to successfully plan, execute, and ship products, and he cares deeply about customers and markets.

EXPERIENCE

rabbit, inc.

Head of Applied AI 20

2024 — Present



Josh leads a team of Applied AIML engineers, working with conversational AI models (LLMs, speech-to-text, text-to-speech) as well as large multimodal models (vision and text). Josh coordinates between various C-level stakeholders from product, research, and engineering teams.

 $Leadership\ Team\ \cdot\ Recruiting\ \cdot\ Strategic\ Partnerships\ \cdot\ Contract\ Negotiations$

Coqui

Co-founder 2021 — 2024



As one of four founders, Josh has been at every stage of the business. From pitching the first VCs, to collecting data for AI models, to red-lining with enterprise customers. In the early days Josh spent most time training speech-to-text models and working on the data pipeline. As the business grew, Josh took on product and GTM leadership.

Board Member · Leadership Team · Go-to-Market Strategy · Product Strategy · $R\&D \cdot B2B$ Sales · Recruiting · Strategic Partnerships · PR and Marketing · Investor Relations · Customer Relations · Contract Negotiations

Mozilla Foundation

Machine Learning Fellow

2020 - 2021



Josh lead the AI strategy for a multi-national multi-stakeholder project to deploy voice technologies in East Africa, aligned with UN Sustainable Development goals. Target applications were a COVID radio monitoring dashboard for the Ugandan Ministry of Health as well as COVID informational voicebot for the Rwandan Information Society Authority. Partners included the German government, Ugandan academia, and the Rwandan startup sector. Josh was involved at every stage of the project, from ideation to pitching stakeholders, from data collection to model training and deployment. Josh developed the first publicly available speech recognition models for the Kinyarwanda and Luganda languages.

Artie, Inc.

Lead Scientist 2019 — 2021



Josh directed and developed all Speech technologies used at Artie. The technologies were integrated into a game engine to power conversational AI avatars. Josh developed the pipeline for data collection and quality control, and he scaled the training of contextually dependent language model decoders for custom speech-to-text engines. Josh also experimented with text-to-speech at the time, but the state-of-the-art wasn't high enough for production use. Josh collected data, trained the core models, and worked with the backend team to deploy.

National Science Foundation

Graduate Research Fellow

2015 - 2019



Josh was awarded 1 out of 10 Fellowships nationally in his category. The Fellowship supported Josh during four years of dissertation research on automatic speech recognition. In particular, Josh worked on algorithms for more efficient training of speech recognition models for new languages. During his research, Josh spent one year in Paris as a research fellow at CNRS, and multiple data collection trips to Kyrgyzstan as a research fellow at the American University of Central Asia.

Mozilla Corporation

Machine Learning Researcher

2018 - 2019



Josh joined the Machine Learning group at Mozilla in order to bring automatic speech recognition to as many languages as possible. He accomplished this by working closely with the data collection team (i.e. Project Common Voice) as well as training end-to-end speech recognition models via multitask and transfer learning with the core ML team (i.e. Project DeepSpeech).

Various Companies

 ${\bf Speech\ Recognition\ Consultant}$

2016 - 2018



Josh worked as an automatic speech recognition consultant, for companies ranging from large telcos to small edtech startups. He designed training and data pipelines, mostly revolving around the Kaldi toolkit. Kaldi was the state-of-the-art in speech recognition before DeepSpeech, and DeepSpeech was state-of-the-art until Whisper.

CNRS

Chateaubriand Research Fellow 2016 — 2017



Josh researched transfer-learning for acoustic models as well as text augmentation for language decoders, both in the context of automatic speech recognition. Over this year at CNRS, Josh cemented his knowledge of the underpinnings of speech recognition. Josh's time at CNRS was supported by the Embassy of France to the United States under a Chateaubriand STEM Fellowship.

American University of Central Asia

Research Fellow 2013 — 2014



During this research fellowship and multiple visits afterward, Josh conducted acoustic-phonetic research on the Kyrgyz language. This included creation of a spoken dataset of Kyrgyz regional varieties, as well as behavioral studies on human perception of both Russian and Kyrgyz by native speakers. In addition, Josh organized a working group on computational linguistics for students, professors, and researchers.

EDUCATION



University of Arizona

2019

Ph.D. in Computational Linguistics

Tucson, AZ

& Thesis: Multi-Task and Transfer Learning in Low-Resource Speech Recognition



University of Arizona

2015

M.A. in Linguistics

Tucson, AZ



Seton Hall University B. A. in Liberal Studies

2012 South Orange, NJ

B.A. in Liberal Studies South Oran

GRANTS & AWARDS

Graduate Research Fellowship	National Science Foundation	\$138,000	2015 — 2019
NSF INTERN Grant	National Science Foundation	\$50,000	2018
Chateaubriand STEM Fellowship	Embassy of France to the USA	€5.000	2016
GROW Travel Award	National Science Foundation	\$5,000	2016
Visiting Research Fellowship	American University of Central Asia	\$5,000	2013 — 2014
Regents Scholarship	Seton Hall University	\$111,140	2008 — 2012
Liberal Studies Honors Citation	Seton Hall University		2012

PUBLICATIONS



XTTS: a Massively Multilingual Zero-Shot Text-to-Speech Model. INTERSPEECH Casanova, E; Davis, K; Gölge, E; Göknar, G; Gulea, I; Hart, L; Aljafari, A; Meyer, 2024 J; Morais, R; Olayemi, S; Weber, J. https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04904

AfroDigits: A Community-Driven Spoken Digit Dataset for African Languages. Emezue, C; Gandhi, S; Tunstall, L; Abid, A; Meyer, J; Lhoest, Q; Allen, P; Von Platen, P; Kiela, D; Jernite, Y; Chaumond, J; Noyan, M.; Sanseviero, O. https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.12582

AfricaNLP 2023 (colocated ICLR 2023)

BibleTTS: A Large, High-fidelity, Multilingual, and Uniquely African Speech Corpus. Meyer, J; Adelani, D; Casanova, E; Öktem, A; Whitenack, D; Weber, J; Kabongo, S; Salesky, E; Orife, I; Leong, C; Ogayo, P; Emezue, C; Mukiibi, J; Osei, S; Agbolo, A; Akinode, V; Opoku, B; Olanrewaju, S; Alabi, J; Muhammad, S. https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.03546

INTERSPEECH 2022

The Makerere Radio Speech Corpus: A Luganda Radio Corpus for Automatic Speech Recognition. Mukiibi, J; Katumba, A; Nakatumba-Nabende, J; Hussein, A; Meyer, J. https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.09790

LREC 2022

Multilingual Spoken Words Corpus. Mazumder, M; Chitlangia, S; Banbury, C; Kang, Y; Ciro, JM; Achorn, K; Galvez, D; Sabini, M; Mattson, P; Kanter, D; Diamos, G; Warden, P; Meyer, J; Reddi, V. https://openreview.net/forum?id=c20jiJ5K2H

NeurIPS 2021 (Datasets and Benchmarks Track)

Few-Shot Keyword Spotting in Any Language. Mazumder, M; Banbury, C; Meyer, J; Warden, P; Reddi, V. https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.01454

INTERSPEECH 2021

What shall we do with an hour of data? Speech recognition for the unand under-served languages of Common Voice. Tyers, F; Meyer, J. https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.04674

2021 arXiv

Common Voice: A Massively-Multilingual Speech Corpus. Ardila, R; Branson, M; Davis, K; Henretty, M; Kohler, M; Meyer, J; Morais, R; Saunders, L; Tyers, F; Weber, G. https://arxiv.org/abs/1912.06670

LREC 2020

Artie Bias Corpus: An Open Dataset for Detecting Demographic Bias in Speech Applications. Meyer, J; Rauchenstein, L; Eisenberg, J; Howell, N. https://aclanthology.org/2020.lrec-1.796/

LREC 2020

Multi-Task and Transfer Learning in Low-Resource Speech Recognition. Meyer, J. http://jrmeyer.github.io/misc/MEYER_dissertation_2019.pdf

2019 PhD Dissertation. University of Arizona.

Unsupervised Task Discovery for Multi-Task Acoustic Modeling. Meyer, J. https://github.com/JRMeyer/mlslp/blob/master/poster/mlslp-poster.pdf

Machine Learning in Speech and Language Processing Workshop (co-located INTERSPEECH 2018)

The Field is not the Lab, and the Lab is not the Field: Experimental linguistics and endangered language communities. Meyer, J; Kloehn, N; Carnie, A. https://www.degruyter.com/document/doi/10.1515/9783110527018/html

2018 De Gruyter Mouton: Insights from Practices in Community-Based Research

Navigating the safety implications of doing research and being researched in Kyrgyzstan: cooperation, networks and framing. Bekmurzaev, N; Lottholz, P; Meyer, J. https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/02634937. 2017.1419165

2018 Central Asian Survey.

Development of a Kyrgyz Speech Synthesizer: A Demonstration of the Ossian Frontend and Merlin Neural Network Speech Synthesis Toolkit. Meyer, J. http://www.turklang.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/%D0%A2.1.pdf

2017 The 5th International Conference on Computer Processing of Turkic Languages

'Friend' or 'Foreign Agent'? On the Limits of Field Research in Post-Soviet Kyrgyzstan. Lottholz, P; Meyer, J. https://www.academia.edu/33980022

2016 Exeter Central Asian Studies Network

Conducting Linguistic Fieldwork in Kyrgyzstan. Meyer, https://journals.uair.arizona.edu/index.php/arizanthro/article/viewFile/21375/20949

J. 2016 Arizona Anthropologist, Vol. 27

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE (OTHER)

Arizona Phonological Imaging Lab. Josh developed software to visualize and statistically analyze ultrasonic images of tongue contours for articulatory-phonetics research.

2015

Arizona Scottish Gaelic Project Josh conducted fieldwork with speakers of Scottish Gaelic, and aided in the compilation of an online grammar for the language.

2012 - 2013

Language Acquisition Research Center at Hunter CUNY. Josh designed a 2011 - 2012text corpus-based research program, transcribed spontaneous child speech, and designed the laboratory's website. KIT/NYU MEG Lab at NYU. Josh aided in the analysis and processing of 2012 Magnetoencephalography (MEG) brain imaging data from cognitive science research. Language Acquisition and Neurolinguistics Lab at Rutgers University. Josh 2012 aided in experimental design of Neurolinguistic research studies. TALKS & PRESENTATIONS Language Technologies in Central Asia: A Survey. Joint ESCAS-CESS Con-2017 ference at the American University of Central Asia. Bishkek. Predicting Language Dominance in Kyrgyz-Russian Bilinguals. w/ Quam, 2015 C. Arizona Linguistics Circle 9. Tucson. Phonological processing in Kyrgyz-Russian bilinguals. w/ Quam, C; Bever, 2014 T. The Miniconference on Metrical Structure: Acquisition and processing. Utrecht. The Kyrgyzstan corpus project: Building a language resource unique to 2014 Kyrgyzstan and available to all. CASI Public Seminar at the American University of Central Asia. Bishkek. Now you hear it, now you don't: Phonological processing in Kyrgyz-2013 Russian bilinguals. CASI Public Seminar at the American University of Central Asia. Bishkek. Psycholinguistics: Thinking about language differently. Lecture conducted 2013 at The Platttform at Werkstatttraum. Berlin. WRITTEN TUTORIALS Kaldi Troubleshooting Head-to-Toe. & Link. 2018 How to Train practically any Model from practically any Data with Ten-2018 sorFlow. @ Link. Getting started with the Merlin Speech Synthesis Toolkit. & Link. 2017 How to Train a Deep Neural Net Acoustic Model with Kaldi. & Link. 2016 How to add a new language to the eSpeak NG Speech Synthesizer. @ Link. 2016 The Flow of TensorFlow: An Email Classification Tutorial. @ Link. 2016 An Introduction to CMU-Sphinx Speech Recognition Toolkit: First Steps. 2016 ∂ Link.

Curriculum Vitae

Joshua Meyer

EVENT ORGANIZATION

Kyrgyz Voice Technology Hackathon . American University of Central Asia. Attended by undergraduate students as well as professional developers. ℰ Link.	2019
DeepSpeech & Common Voice Tutorial . <i>University of Tartu</i> . Delivered to attendees of the Fifth International Workshop on Computational Linguistics for Uralic Languages. <i>P</i> Link.	2019
Speech Synthesis Workshop: Hands-on with Merlin & Ossian. Higher School of Economics. Delivered to Computational Linguistics Faculty and Graduate Students. ℰ Link.	
Speech Recognition Workshop: Hands-on with Kaldi & DeepSpeech. Higher School of Economics. Delivered to Computational Linguistics Faculty and Graduate Students. & Link.	2017

OPEN SOURCE WORK

Coqui STT T	rained Coqui's best STT model on 47k hours of data. ♂ Link.	2021
Mozilla DeepSpeech	$Added\ Transfer\ Learning.\ \mathscr{D}\ Link.$	2020
Multi-Task Kaldi	$\textit{Multi-Task Acoustic Modeling. } \mathcal{E} \ \text{Link}.$	2018
NVDA	Added Kyrgyz language to screen reader. ${\mathscr E}$ Link.	2017
eSpeak NG	Added Kyrgyz language to speech synthesizer. ${\mathscr E}$ Link.	2016
Autotrace	Created visualization tools for ultrasonic imaging. ${\mathscr E}$ Link.	2015

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Computer Languages Python, Bash, MATLAB, Perl, R, C++ (some knowledge)

Other TensorFlow, PyTorch (some knowledge), Kaldi, scikit-learn, pandas,

nltk, matplotlib, kenlm, Linux, AWS, git, GitHub